can you buy
[Music]
and all our faithful people on social
media people on our website people on
YouTube people on Facebook we want to
welcome you all and we want to welcome
especially as well all the people here
give yourselves a big hand everybody
amen
we are thankful to be here together in
the presence of the Lord hallelujah
first Thessalonians 5 19 is our main
text
a short verse quenched not the spirit
I won't go back to everything that we
have
said but we're using this as a theme for
this month quench not the spirit but
fan into Flame
versatility 5 19 the King James version
quenched not the spirit the word quench
as we noted last week it means to
extinguish
figuratively or literally when you
extinguish oh it's like when you when
you when you blow out a lit candle
or when you pour water over
burning fire
to extinguish it
and Paul says don't quench the spirit
it doesn't quench the spirit when the
spirit wants to work Among Us
when the Holy Spirit inspires us to
worship God born
when you sense the spirit move in your
life move in your heart
don't
douse him out and pour water over it by
being unresponsive
quench not the spirit
we are a spirit people spirit-led people
Spirit-filled people
we respond to the spirit yeah
foreign
we are not afraid to declare it because
we know what the spirit can do in one
second
can transform everything about us
the Holy Spirit can go back into history
go back Generations before us
go back to our fathers and our
forefathers and the mistakes and the
wrongs that happened back then
go back into a family that is destroyed
and a family that's of course and the
spirit in a second
can put back on costs what is of course
when the spirit is at work
so we don't want to quench the spirit
we want to respond to the spirit
can I hear an amen
read this from the Amplified Bible and I
loved it and I borrowed it in the
Amplified Bible do not quench subdue or
be unresponsive
to the working and guidance of the Holy
Spirit
see the holy spirit will not force you
and insist
but he will prompt you
he will inspire you he'll give you a
gentle push it's up to you to respond
so instead of us quenching the spirit
were encouraged in second Timothy 1 6 to
stare up
the gift of God
or to fend it into flame while the Holy
Spirit is prompting us to do let's have
more of the Holy Spirit more of his
prompting more of his power when the
holy spirit moves you in a certain
directions and he begins to work in your
life allow him to permeate you allow him
to saturate you allow the direction of
the Holy Spirit to be the only way you
live get worse in loving God get worse
in praying get worse in reading the
Bible get worse in Walking In Holiness
get worse in hearing the voice of God
just allow the spirit in your life
instead of putting out their spirit
Paul said this to Timothy because
apparently this young man according to
what Paul says in chapter 4 verse 14 he
was neglecting the gift
that was in him and Paul is reminding
him
fan it into Flame
keep it at full flame what God is has
given you as a gift and what God has
given in your life so we take this as an
exhortation that is speaking to us that
we should fend into flame where the Holy
Spirit wants to do so today I want to
talk about Fanning into Flame the spirit
of discipline because you see the Holy
Spirit as much as is the spirit of power
and is the spirit of love but it is also
the spirit that brings discipline into
our lives and so discipline comes into
our lives because God wants us to
develop or cultivate spiritual Fitness I
want to share that with you so let's go
back to Second Timothy 1 verse 1 to
verse 7 and I'm going to read it and I
want you to note we've read it already
but I want to read more verses there
Paul an apostle of Christ Jesus and I'm
reading the NIV by the will of God
according to the prom of life that is in
Christ Jesus to Timothy my dear son
grace mercy and peace from God the
father and Christ Jesus our lord I thank
God for myself as my forefathers did
with a clear conscience as night and day
I constantly remember you in my prayers
recalling your tears I long to see you
so that I may be filled with joy I've
been reminded of your sincere Faith with
first lived in your grandmother Louis
and in your mother Eunice and I am
persuaded now that Faith lives in you
also now here we go verse six for this
reason I remind you Timothy to Fan into
Flame the gift of God which is in you
through the laying on of my hands now
note verse 7 for God did not give us a
spirit of timidity but a spirit of power
a spirit of love and a spirit of
self-discipline somebody say
self-discipline
to look at your neighbor say neighbor I
think you need self-discipline
now I'm joking I'm joking just say
self-discipline
now you know masalana sometimes when you
look at what people do in the name of
being led by the spirit
you you get surprised
the holy spirit is the spirit of
self-discipline
and he stands within us self-discipline
you can never be able to be all that you
need to be as a Christian if you lack
discipline in your life
you know sometimes people want to kill
our lucky boy about the things that they
are doing even the Moya doesn't
understand what these people are doing
I remember one guy came to my dad years
ago which is
my dad says hey I don't mind
it just depends which Maya is holding
you
tell your neighbor it just depends which
Maya is holding you
but you see if is holding you and if
it's the Holy Spirit you will be
disciplined and you'll have discipline
in your life somebody say discipline
I can see the amens are not much because
you're talking about discipline
First Corinthians chapter 9 verse 25 and
26 I'm reading the good news translation
and Paul here
draws a parallel between athletes
and us as Christians
and he says in the same way athletes
have to embrace certain things certain
disciplines do certain things we need to
do the same thing spiritually
so he says every athlete in training
submits to strict discipline somebody
say strict discipline
how each other you believe in himself
and I restrict discipline
look at your neighbor and say never kiss
trick discipline why are you Whispering
it's strict discipline
all right so every athlete submits not
just to discipline but strict discipline
why
in order to be crowned with a wreath
which will not last
but we do it for one that will last
forever
foreign
First Timothy 4 7
in the Amplified Bible
writing to Timothy
he says and I read the Amplified Bible
train yourself
towards godliness so you know godliness
living for God demands discipline
training
not what he says he says train yourself
towards godliness
keeping yourself spiritually fit
there are a lot of God's people who are
unfit spiritually
they're not fit because they haven't
dispel of discipline
they are not in any way working hard now
cultivating spiritual discipline
is a trait that we must have
God will move you into discipline
he will challenge you into a disciplined
life so we need to fend into Flame
spiritual disciplines we need to
cultivate and fend into flame discipline
into our lives it's something we must
encourage it's something we must learn
for is something we must work hard for
you must not allow yourself to be
undisciplined in praying and disciplined
in reading the Bible and disciplined in
the way you live and disciplined in your
appetites and discipline in the way you
talk and disciplined in the way you use
money and disciplined in the thoughts
you allow in your mind and disciplined
in the relationship you have and
discipline in where you do what you use
your body for this body is a temple of
the Holy Spirit you you have no time to
put this body into things it shouldn't
come into we need to be disciplined God
has given us a spirit of discipline
self-discipline and that is one of the
major traits of being a spiritually
matured person is to be self-disciplined
look at your neighbor and saying
John Maxwell says this about discipline
and I quote
he says discipline in the beginning of
Life
is a chance of achieving what you really
want by doing things you really don't
want to do
[Music]
when they showed you certain things to
do that were right they don't feel good
sometimes when you go on a diet the
thing they tell you to eat nearly you
know
you don't like it doesn't have taste but
if you stick with the program
and you are disciplined and you don't
get tempted chocolate the ice cream is
why
chocolate chocolate ice cream I don't
know why I guess I'll be like I don't
know why I'm forward to sing when I come
up in the house not just I don't know
why
but you know discipline and let me
finish the quotation discipline in the
beginning of Life is the chance of
achieving what you really want by doing
things you don't really want to do
continues to say after successfully
doing this for some time
discipline becomes the choice of
achieving what you really want by doing
things you now want to do
yeah
that's true
then he says I truly believe we can
become disciplined and enjoy it after
years of practicing it
do you realize how hard it was for you
to come back to church after lockdown
some people are still locked down even
now
some people still make excuses for not
coming to church
I'll tell him my Bishop just now during
the break I was talking to somebody from
one church and we'd really talk to the
to the pastor there to say
you know
let people come to church and this
person no whatever finally opened the
church so I was talking to one of the
past I said how are things going on
yeah he said you know people come but
they don't all come the sound system
this is not working that's not working
again
you see what we have what many of us
haven't realized is to see how we can
easily lose our discipline
and how hard it is to come back
some of you you direct yourself to
church this morning you are still
sleeping
look at your sleeping neighbor and say
yeah
we realized when we when we first came
back some of you I remember when you
first came back you didn't even know how
to praise God anymore look at the
wonderful worship that we had today
few Sanders ago where were you
huh
so I'm just trying to show you about
something discipline is something you
can build into your life it can become
pun and parcel of your DNA pardon parcel
of what you do such that you end up
enjoying it some of you you jog
regularly you enjoy it even when you run
out there
enjoy your own and outside Joker you can
see you didn't go there you didn't go to
the gym same way you can miss prayer you
can miss church
you can miss reading the Bible you miss
these things they are part and parcel of
your discipline can I hear an amen
discipline
places greater value on Essentials
orders is priorities intelligently
operates by schedule
functions without constant supervision
and makes the most of the time
let me say that again discipline
places greater value and Essentials when
you're a disciplined person you have no
time for non-essential things
some of you you are burning up your time
in things that have no value
fighting battles you shouldn't be
fighting picking up conversations you
shouldn't even be talking go into places
you shouldn't be going reading stuff
that you shouldn't be reading
you know people just trust me you know
you know several times you've ended up
in the newspaper for all the wrong
reasons and not not because we did
anything
and people were asking me you didn't
respond good I
why
there are people
rise up
how am I gonna Help Church doesn't
matter what you tell treasury will
treasurize so leave the instructions to
shut your eyes I'm not sure Rising
unfundi so I just go foreign
[Applause]
what has changed
some of you
in a thick a thick skin to let people
talk and not respond
what
Barcelona there are things I don't have
time for
do you understand what I'm saying to you
there are things you mustn't have time
for you are wasting your precious time
you are wasting your precious money you
are wasting I'm telling you Barcelona
you always you are wasting your airtime
control mix
disciplined places
greater value on essential
discipline orders his priorities
intelligently when you're a disciplined
person you have easy to that we call
priorities
there are things that come first
you don't just rush into your life into
the day who says
things like prayer you should never ever
have a day where you never prayed
you should never have a day where you
never read God's word never
you should never ever deal where you
haven't watched
[Applause]
isn't it strange Barcelona there's many
people who are achieving things when the
rest of people are always saying I
didn't have time
people who live in the same time frame
as you
they are doing stuff they are achieving
things you are saying
it's not about not having time it's
about what you prioritize if you really
can look at your life look at the things
that you give time to
tell me if you don't have time
I I like the way you are quiet
three a disciplined life operates by
schedule
gotta have a schedule
could you order your day
even when you rest
on purpose
and then trying to rest up from the rest
some people
number four a discipline functions
without constant supervision
to be threatened and supervised all the
time it's undisciplined people
when you're disciplined you don't you
don't supervise you supervise yourself
it's called self-leadership
[Music]
self-leadership
and then
discipline number five makes the most of
the time when you are a disciplined
person you'll achieve a lot in life
it says God has given us the spirit of
self-discipline
I think for me this is one why I was so
turned off as a young person in the
early days and I didn't understand
people who say
and I was almost turned off to being
responsive to the holy spirit because of
what people used to do in the name of
the spirit
the whole day
happier
conference in the whole day the whole
week
foreign
[Music]
service service that day
I think about half past ten in the
evening
so when I went out the ministry saw me
she said praise God
so now I want to know now praise God for
what
it says
LED you to me so that you must give me a
lift
oh yeah
that's why that's why that's why people
revive
I
know
foreign
[Applause]
because of the baby
and this conference was in randburg
um
those years
with a baby
so as I drove this person tells me the
way
and I'm listening
then then
and then then I find out go to Los
Saturn actually is the husband
Ninja
I said to him if I was married to you
the way you are behaving I didn't spare
her
he said this man doesn't know Christ not
born again do you think this kind of
behavior of yours
do you think this way of Behaving
Hallelujah
okay which Maya is holding you now
see there's lots of people who do all
kinds of things
under the guise of being led by the
spirit
yeah but see the Holy Spirit you look at
the Life of Christ disciplined life
as a man if you are led by the spirit
you will be a disciplined man
disciplined man you will not abuse your
wife
disciplined life you take care of your
family
disciplined life
the amens are not there maybe they're
not on TV you are saying amen maybe
they're not on TV I mean
I mean now note
it starts first with a disciplined life
before we can cultivate spiritual
Fitness
because even with Fitness
you must get ready to get into a fitness
problem program and invest in your
Fitness
now you know if you've ever built your
natural muscles you know that it takes
time
to get to certain levels it doesn't
happen overnight to get into shape to
pick up extra muscles to be toned 90
December years or maybe they'll open the
beaches we don't know
so if you want to have a beach body
foreign
the truth is this if you're only going
to start this month you're already late
particularly if we have extra extra what
you call it to deal with
it's a bit late to have a six-pack right
now unless you are lean messed already
at least you might but you should have
worked out much earlier you should have
started in July but nevertheless I still
encourage you to try no but but if you
if if you want to have a beach body
right right you know you have to really
work and it has to be an organized
program and you can't skip your training
you don't have to train every day but
you have to train enough to start
dealing with the extra watch whatever
okay if you start with weights and you
want to build up muscle you start with
light weights you can't go now guys neh
and gonna try and bench press 100 cages
all right so you start with and then you
gradually work your way up to a heavier
weight
it doesn't happen overnight but then
remember as you train there will be days
where your body feels sore and your body
will preach to you we can't go back
there
so what do you do you have to tell your
body you see
people who are not disciplined are ruled
by what their body tells them
if they don't feel like praying pray
they don't pray if they don't feel like
reading the Bible they don't read the
Bible they're just ruled by how they
feel but you know very well with an
exercise program you still have to go in
fact you see these people running much
you see these guys playing soccer they
are strapped up but they are playing
there
so you need to do that so it's important
for us that we do that it needs
dedication it needs persistence it needs
Focus the Bible tells us that even if
there's value in physical training
but you know spiritual training is of
more value
ah no you don't like my sermon anymore
1 Timothy 4 7 and 8 says but rejoked
reject profane and old wife's fables and
exercise yourself
towards godliness for bodily exercise
profits little
so it has a profit to exercise your body
Maria is little because it just deals
with your physical body
he says but godliness
godliness
is profitable for us and now you know
when you are healthy and you are fit
there's a lot of benefits your mind is
sharp you've got stamina you know your
heart is beating right you know your
blood sugar levels are down if you are
eating right you know everything is well
your feet you're good you know you know
sickness your your immune system is up
all those benefits much as good as good
as they can be they can never equal the
benefit of being spiritually fit
he says bodily he says being spiritually
fit godliness exercising yourself in
godliness is profitable in all things
what does he mean he says when you are
spiritually fit it will flow over into
all areas of your life
because the state of your spiritual life
has a way of affecting everything about
you it affects you in your vision it
affects you in your goals it affects you
in your thinking it affects the way you
talk it affects you in the way you
handle money it affects your body it
affects the way you live it your level
of happiness and contentment it affects
the facts and about your life it affects
how you plan it
I saw your your views about life it
affects the way you look at life
godliness is profitable in all things
you become stronger you become more
powerful you are more happier you praise
the Lord even more can I hear a good
amen in the house godliness
godliness and the prophet of godliness
because what you have sowed in godliness
flows over into your family flows over
into the Next Generation so you might as
well be fit spiritually
they fit spiritually
can I hear an amen
my time is gone
the time is gone Eric finally getting
stop
page now
let me finish off quickly it says in the
Amplified Bible says but refuse and
avoid irreverent Legends profane and
pure and Godless fictions mere
grandmother's tales and sillimet and
express your disapproval of them now
note train yourself towards godliness
piety keeping yourself spiritually fit
verse 8 for physical training is of some
value it's useful for a little but
godliness spiritual training is useful
and is value in everything and and in
every way but not the last part and it
holds the promise
for the present life
and also for the life which is to come
you can't think about it
think about it how you're discipline of
being a Praying Woman
open a praying man
how not only benefits you now it
benefits your children and your
children's children not only benefits
you on this Earth it benefits you even
for the life that is to come think about
it when you got on the word of God and
started Living by the word of God look
at how that affects you look at how that
affects your children and your
children's children look how it affects
your family look how it affects your
great grandchildren but most of all look
how it affects even the world to come
oh yeah
it's worth us Barcelona being
spiritually fit
and we fit spiritually
now notice I close
exercising your spirit
will strengthen your spiritual muscles
the stronger you are spiritually
the easier it will be for you
to do all the things that God instructs
us to do in line with the disciplines we
find in Scripture
wow
to be easier for you to work in
forgiveness
to walk in faith
to walk in the anointing
to subdue the power of the devil
just like it is in the natural when you
are fit when a bully comes to fight you
you take them down
and you know very well when the bullet
comes to fight you that's not the time
to start the training program
when the bullet comes to fight you you
must have already started the program
in other words you don't wait for
trouble to come before you get strong
in the same way when you are spiritually
fit when troubles comes When Trials come
you stand up strong in the Lord and in
the power of his mind and so we need
therefore to build our spiritual muscles
and we are going to learn about that
next week
because we can't do it today for the
sake of time may the Lord bless the
reading of his word and the preaching of
his word come on give the Lord a big
kind of praise
come on somebody give the Lord a big
hand of praise
Hallelujah Give the Lord a big kind of
praise
I've got a question for you are you
going to be spiritually fit if your
answer he said yes give the Lord a big
kind of Praise are you going to be
filled are you going to make sure you
have a program a spiritual program and
you're going to get on your health
program on your fitness program and
you're not going to you're not going to
compromise on it